[{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"1. During this battle, Ameinias failed to capture an enemy commander who held a ten-thousand drachma bounty for the insolence of being a woman. At this battle, the victorious leader had his slave Sicinnus feign defection in order to lure the enemy into position. The losing commander built a throne on Mount Aigaleo to observe this battle, which was fought after a stalemate at Artemisium. Queen Artemisia of Halicarnassus escaped this battle by ramming her ship into friendly forces. For 10 points, name this 480 B.C. defeat of Xerxes’ Persian navy by an allied Greek fleet under the command of Themistocles. ","answer":"ANSWER: Battle of Salamis "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"2. In a play by this author, the sudden withering of some roses represents the demise of the title spinster, who waits over twenty years for her fiance to return. This author wrote a play in which a mother is reminded of her husband’s death by her son’s request for a knife; in that play, Death takes the form of an old beggar woman while the Moon is represented by a young woodcutter. Near the end of that work by this playwright, Leonardo Felix and the Groom kill each other. This author’s best known play features an all-female cast, and concerns a matriarch who institutes a lengthy mourning period for her second husband. For 10 points, name this Spanish playwright of Blood Wedding and The House of Bernarda Alba. ","answer":"ANSWER: Federico Garcia Lorca "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"3. People of this profession are depicted in the best-known portraits of photographer Barbara Morgan. It’s not acting, but a woman of this profession named Moira Shearer plays Vicky Page in Powell and Pressburger’s film The Red Shoes. Marie van Goethem, a 14-year old girl of this profession, is depicted in an 1880 wax sculpture by an artist who also painted one of these people in Fin d'Arabesque. People of this profession like Misty Copeland often practice Pierre Beauchamp’s five positions. Edgar Degas painted two young girls of this profession Practicing at the Barre. For 10 points, name this artistic profession whose female practitioners traditionally wear tutus. ","answer":"ANSWER: ballet dancers [or ballerinas; prompt on dancers] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"4. This religion’s prophets preached at halls called samavasaranas after achieving a state called kevala jnana [“KAY-vuh-luhj NAW-nuh”]. Five auspicious events known as Panch Kalyanaka are associated with the lives of this religion’s prophets. This religion’s last major historical figure preached the principle of anekantavada, or many-sided reality, and had his teachings compiled into the Agamas. A broom, a gourd, and a book of scripture are the only possessions held by the naked monks of this religion’s Digambara sect. This religion’s last tirthankara, Mahavira, preached observance of the five vows. For 10 points, name this Indian religion that emphasizes a form of nonviolence called ahimsa. ","answer":"ANSWER: Jainism [or Jain Dharma] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"5. It’s not scattering, but this phenomenon can cause anti-Stokes lines when the starting molecule is already in an excited state. The decay of this process can be accomplished through Dexter electron transfer or Förster resonance energy transfer. The intensity of this process can be reduced by quenching. The quantum yield of this process is equal to the ratio of the number of photons emitted and the number of photons absorbed. This process names lamps that use mercury vapor to emit light. This process names a form of microscopy that often makes use of GFP. For 10 points, name this form of luminescence in which photons are absorbed and then emitted at a lower energy. ","answer":"ANSWER: fluorescence [accept word forms] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"6. Particularly violent examples of these groups, such as the Cossacks and the Comancheros, are often referred to as “one-percenters.” Alexander Zaldostanov leads a Vladimir Putin-backed group of this type, The Night Wolves, that participated in the annexation of Crimea. One of these groups was allegedly paid in beer to provide security at the Altamont Free Concert, where they caused a riot during The Rolling Stones’ performance. Mayans MC is a spin-off of an FX Network show about a fictional one of these groups, the Sons of Anarchy. The Bandidos and the Hell’s Angels are examples of, for 10 points, what criminal groups whose members often ride Harley Davidsons? ","answer":"ANSWER: outlaw motorcycle gangs [accept outlaw motorcycle clubs or biker gangs or other reasonable descriptive answers] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"7. The plot of one of this author’s novels is compared to the allegations of the Casement Report in an Adam Hochschild book. Tayeb Salih’s Season of Migration to the North is often interpreted as a rebuttal to this author. In Dreams from My Father, Barack Obama says that this author’s most famous novel is “not about black people” but this man’s perspective. This author is called a “thoroughgoing racist” in an essay that claims his depiction of Africa “is to Europe as the picture is to Dorian Gray.” Chinua Achebe’s “An Image of Africa” attacks this author’s use of racist tropes in a novel that ends with Kurtz’s death. For 10 points, name this author of Heart of Darkness. ","answer":"ANSWER: Joseph Conrad [or Jozef Teodor Konrad Korzeniowski] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"8. After arming followers of this movement in Wales, William Price fled to France and became an archdruid. Thomas Carlyle raised the “Condition of England” question in a pamphlet titled for this movement. A march on the Westgate Hotel led by John Frost to free supporters of this movement culminated in the Newport Rising. Feargus O’Connor propagated this movement in his newspaper, The Northern Star. William Lovett helped draft this movement’s namesake document, which included calls for compensating MPs and secret ballots among its six demands. For 10 points, name this working-class movement that sought universal male suffrage in Britain. ","answer":"ANSWER: Chartists [or Chartism] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"9. Xenon monochloride can be used to create the excimer type of these devices. These devices were used by Arthur Ashkin to manipulate small particles, winning him the 2018 Nobel Prize in Physics for the development of optical tweezers. Theodore Maiman developed the first of these devices, which used ruby as a gain medium. Arthur Kastler invented the technique of optical pumping, which is used in these devices to achieve a population inversion. The Einstein A and B coefficients describe processes that occur in these devices, including spontaneous and stimulated emission. For 10 points, name these devices that emit a beam of coherent light. ","answer":"ANSWER: lasers [accept lamps before “Arthur” is read; prompt on optical tweezers before read] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"0. Galen Strawson asserts that this concept leads to an infinite regression in his “Basic Argument” against this concept. Alvin Plantinga’s defense against the argument from evil is named for this concept. Daniel Dennett’s Elbow Room uses intuition pumps to explain this concept. Duration is defined as “the immediate data of consciousness” in a Henri Bergson book titled for Time and this concept. Compatibilist philosophers argue that this concept and determinism are not mutually exclusive. For 10 points, name this philosophical concept, the ability to choose between possible actions. ","answer":"ANSWER: free will "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"1. Court cases involving this practice often use a test coined by Earl Warren’s majority opinion in Tropp v. Dulles, the “evolving standards of decency” test. When given a scenario about his wife Kitty, Michael Dukakis defended his opposition to this practice during a presidential debate. Roper v. Simmons established that this practice cannot be imposed on juveniles. A notoriously faulty device nicknamed “Old Sparky” was used to perform this practice in Florida. The majority opinion to Furman v. Georgia, which briefly suspended this practice in the United States, concluded that this practice is always “cruel and unusual punishment.” For 10 points, name this practice of executing criminals. ","answer":"ANSWER: capital punishment [or the death penalty; or execution until it is read; accept more specific types of capital punishment like the electric chair or lethal injection; prompt on cruel and unusual punishment until read] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"2. Samuel Butler argued that this book was written by a Sicilian woman. Emily Wilson’s 2018 translation of this book emphasizes its protagonist’s role as a “complicated man” by describing him as a “wily lord of lies.” Poems from the perspective of twelve hanged maids are interspersed throughout Margaret Atwood’s modern interpretation of this book. The last chapter of a novel inspired by this book is a soliloquy in which a woman exclaims “yes I said yes I will Yes;” that woman is Molly Bloom and that chapter is entitled “Penelope.” James Joyce’s Ulysses is a retelling of, for 10 points, what Homeric epic?. ","answer":"ANSWER: the Odyssey "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"3. A Trojan hero who is invulnerable to spear and sword turned into one of these animals after he was strangled to death by Achilles. The son of Sthenelus turned into one of these animals out of grief after the death of his lover Phaethon. Ares turned Alectryon into one of these animals because he fell asleep guarding Ares and Aphrodite. Heracles shoots many these animals with arrows from the Hydra as part of his sixth labor; those are the Stymphalian types of these animals. Castor and Pollux were born after Leda was impregnated by Zeus in the form of one of these animals. For 10 points, cygnus and apus are what kind of flying animal? ","answer":"ANSWER: birds [accept swans; accept roosters] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"4. Natural toxicants produced in this plant include chaconine and other glycoalkaloids. In the 1950s many Warsaw Pact countries attempted to eradicate a yellow-striped beetle from Colorado that damaged this plant. A disease that affects this plant is caused by the water mold Phytophthora infestans, Possible ancestors of this crop include Solanum brevicaule, which is native to the Andes Mountains. At 300 million more tons per year than the eggplant and tomato, this crop is the highest produced nightshade plant. For 10 points, late blight affects what plant whose tuber is harvested for use in foods such as French fries? ","answer":"ANSWER: potato plant [or Solanum tuberosum; prompt on spud or tater or other informal terms] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"5. An artist who visited this city was influenced by Raphael Mengs and Johann Winckelmann’s studies of its artworks. A painting contrasts a resident of this city, who broods in the shadows on the left, with his wife and daughters, who mourn as men “bring [him] the bodies of his sons.” In a painting set in this city, the central figure is framed in the center of three arches as his three sons salute the swords he is holding. Students at this city’s French Academy vied for its namesake “Prix” and made sketches of sculptures like The Dying Gladiator and Laocoön. For 10 points, French Neoclassicists like Jacques-Louis David were inspired by the art of Greece and what Italian city, the setting of David’s Oath of the Horatii? ","answer":"ANSWER: Rome "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"6. One of this man’s books caused a scandal in Germany when it was advertised on the jerseys of the ECD Iserlohn hockey team. The Lebanese Shia leader Musa al-Sadr is believed to have died at the hands of this leader, who developed the Third International Theory and the Jamahiriya political system. This leader’s adopted daughter Hana may have died during Operation El Dorado Canyon, which Ronald Reagan ordered in response to his 1986 bombing of a West Berlin discotheque. This author of The Green Book died in 2011 after his regime was overthrown during the Arab Spring. For 10 points, name this longtime dictator of Libya. ","answer":"ANSWER: Muammar Al-Gaddafi [also accept Moammar Gadhafi or Muanmar Khadaf] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"7. A low frequency response exhibited by these devices known as the “proximity effect” may be common if they employ a directional or cardioid polar pattern. Small examples of these devices known as lavaliers can be mounted using clips. Gerhard Sessler of Bell Labs invented the common “electret” type of these devices, which uses a permanently charged material to record changes in air pressure. The “dynamic” type of these devices, which contains an induction coil connected to a diaphragm, uses an operating principle similar to that of loudspeakers. For 10 points, sound waves are converted to electrical signals by what devices that increase a speaker’s volume? ","answer":"ANSWER: microphones [or mics; accept electret microphones; accept dynamic microphones] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"7. Much of this country’s crude oil deposits are located in a 5,100 square mile tidal bay that has a notable duckweed infestation. Angel Falls is in this country, and its central llanos region is irrigated by the Orinoco River. Lake Maracaibo is located in, for 10 points, what country whose capital is Caracas? ","answer":"ANSWER: Venezuela "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"9. A symphony by this composer uses a motif in which the winds play A major and A minor triads over a marchlike timpani rhythm. The word “ewig” [“EE-vig”] is repeatedly sung at the end of this composer’s setting of Hans Bethge’s translations of Chinese poetry. A solo trumpet plays a C-sharp minor fanfare in the opening funeral march of a symphony by this composer whose fourth movement is titled “Urlicht.” Another symphony by this composer includes three “hammer blows of fate” and a theme named for his wife, Alma. For 10 points, name this composer of symphonies nicknamed “Titan” and “Resurrection,” as well as the “Symphony of a Thousand.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Gustav Mahler "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"0. A Henry Louis Gates book titled for the Trials of this poet discusses how Thomas Jefferson tried to undermine this poet’s reputation. This poet, who argued that anyone “may be refin’d, and join th’angelic train,” describes “a celestial choir enthron’d in realms of light” in a poem that praises “Columbia’s scenes of glorious toil.” This writer claimed that “Twas mercy brought me from my pagan land” in a poem that preceded a work dedicated to “His Excellency” George Washington. For 10 points, name this poet who wrote about her experience being taken to the United States as a slave in “On Being Brought from Africa to America.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Phillis Wheatley Tiebreaker. During this war, Thomas Egenton Hogg was arrested for plotting to seize the Panama Railroad Company’s Salvador steamer. A commerce raider fired the last shots of this war off the coast of Alaska five months before surrendering on the River Mersey. John Ericsson designed a ship with a rotating turret at the behest of Gideon Welles during this war, whose captured shipping led Charles Francis Adams to negotiate settlement of the Alabama Claims. One admiral during this war ordered his ships to “damn the torpedoes!” at the Battle of Mobile Bay; that man was David Farragut. For 10 points, name this war in which the ironclads Monitor and Merrimack clashed off Hampton Roads. "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"1. John O’Keeffe received a 2014 Nobel for identifying cells in this structure that activate when a certain environment is encountered. For 10 points each: [10]Name this structure that contains the dentate gyrus. Long-term potentiation was first discovered in this structure. ","answer":"ANSWER: hippocampus [10]Damage to the dentate gyrus has been shown to induce the “anterograde” form of this condition of excessive memory loss. "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this Dutch Golden Age painter of the aforementioned masterpiece, Girl with a Pearl Earring. ","answer":"ANSWER: Johannes Vermeer "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] This artist’s Portrait of Adele Bloch-Bauer is nicknamed “Vienna’s Mona Lisa.” This foremost member of the Vienna Secession made heavy use of gold leaf in paintings like The Kiss. ","answer":"ANSWER: Gustav Klimt "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"0. ","answer":"ANSWER: the Sea of Galilee [or The Storm on the Sea of Galilee] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name these Occitan heretics, based in Southern France, who were massacred at Béziers during an early 13 th -century crusade led by Simon de Montfort the Elder. ","answer":"ANSWER: Cathars [or Albigensians] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Known as gitanos in Spain, these speakers of the Caló language were persecuted in a Great Round-Up ordered by Ferdinand VI. Centuries later, these people were rounded up and massacred during the Porajmos ","answer":"ANSWER: Romani [or Roma; or Gypsies; or Kalé] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] This minority group, whose Sephardic communities populated Iberia, was expelled from Spain by Ferdinand and Isabella’s Alhambra Decree. In Medieval Europe, these people were often accused of using Christian children’s blood to make matzah. ","answer":"ANSWER: Jews [or Jewish people; or Judaism] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this concept that was also divided into multiple categories by Howard Gardner. The Stanford-Binet scale measures its “quotient.” ","answer":"ANSWER: intelligence "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] The self, the world, and the future comprise a “cognitive triad” Aaron Beck proposed to understand beliefs associated with this condition. Dysthymia is a less-severe form of this condition that is often treated with SSRIs. ","answer":"ANSWER: clinical depression "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Mary Ainsworth’s “Strange Situation” experiment helped establish three primary forms of this concept: secure, insecure, and ambivalent. These relationships are key to a theory pioneered by John Bowlby. ","answer":"ANSWER: attachments [or attachment theory] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Timothy Findley coined the name for an “Ontario” version of this genre which, in America, was exemplified in by the work of Carson McCullers and the short story “A Good Man is Hard to Find.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Southern Gothic [accept Southern Ontario Gothic] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Naomi Nakane reconstructs her memory of the Canadian rendition of this historical event in Joy Kogawa’s Obasan. American characters named “Mother”and “Father” are separated during this event in a Julie Otsuka novel. ","answer":"ANSWER: Japanese internment during World War II [prompt on World War II] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] This author couldn’t drive into Canada because his poodle, Charley, didn’t have the right shots. He wrote The Grapes of Wrath. ","answer":"ANSWER: John Steinbeck "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name these figures that are known as malak in Islam. Two of these figures named Munkar and Nakir ask three questions during barzakh. ","answer":"ANSWER: angels [prompt on mala’ikah] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Munkar and Nakir’s questions can only be answered correctly if one truly believes in this Islamic creed, which is one of the Five Pillars of Islam. It states that there is no God but God, and that Muhammad is God’s prophet. ","answer":"ANSWER: shahada [or aš-šahādah] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Reciting the shahada is one of the Five Pillars of Islam along with salat, which requires adherents to pray five times a day facing this holiest city of Islam. ","answer":"ANSWER: Mecca [or Makkah] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this King of Norway who died fighting for the throne of England against Harold Godwinson at the Battle of Stamford Bridge. ","answer":"ANSWER: Harald Hardrada [or Harald III; prompt on Harald] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] As a young man, Harald served with the Varangian Guard in this city as a personal bodyguard to Emperor Michael IV. This city was the capital of the Byzantine Empire. ","answer":"ANSWER: Constantinople "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Having amassed significant wealth from his Varangian loot, Harald stored it in this city, which was ruled by his ally Yaroslav the Wise. A polity based in this city was ruled by the Rurik dynasty. ","answer":"ANSWER: Kiev [or Kievan Rus] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this country where Bo Bardi designed the Sao Paulo Museum of Art. Lucio Costa and Oscar Niemeyer designed this country’s capital city. ","answer":"ANSWER: Brazil "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Bo Bardi published an influential architectural magazine of this name during the 1950s. For Montreal’s Expo 67, Moshe Safdie tried to “reinvent the apartment” with a prefabricated modular housing complex of this name. ","answer":"ANSWER: Habitat [or Habitat 67] [10] 4 blue pilotis support a residence of this name Bo Bardi designed for herself. Ludwig Mies van der Rohe’s Farnsworth House inspired the choice of material used for Philip Johnson’s personal residence, which has this name. "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name these events that are often accompanied by coronal mass ejections. Unlike coronal mass ejections, they emit electromagnetic radiation rather than mass. ","answer":"ANSWER: solar flares [or sun flares; prompt on flares] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Solar flares may interact with the Earth’s magnetosphere to produce these colorful displays of light in the sky, which are termed “borealis” if they occur near the North Pole. ","answer":"ANSWER: auroras [or aurorae; accept aurora borealis] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Independently of Richard Hodgson, this British amateur astronomer made the first observation of a solar flare in 1859 by studying a massive geomagnetic storm that bears his name. ","answer":"ANSWER: Richard Christopher Carrington [or Carrington event; or Carrington storm] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this substance that also titles a novel by Patrick Süskind in which Jean-Baptiste Grenouille, an orphan in 18th-century France, begins murdering pubescent girls to create a perfect variety of it. ","answer":"ANSWER: perfume [or Jitterbug Perfume or Perfume: The Story of a Murderer or Das Parfum] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] The narrator remarks “the smell and taste of things remain poised a long time, like souls” after one of these food items triggers involuntary memories at the opening of Marcel Proust’s In Search of Lost Time. ","answer":"ANSWER: a madeleine [prompt on “cake” or “cookie”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Gustav von Aschenbach detects the strong smell of disinfectant and learns of the cholera epidemic plaguing this Italian city in a Thomas Mann novel. ","answer":"ANSWER: Venice [or Death in Venice or Der Tod in Venedig] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this sitcom that won a GLAAD Award for an episode in which characters shout “not that there’s anything wrong with that!” to deny being gay. This show spawned the catchphrases “no soup for you” and “Serenity Now!” ","answer":"ANSWER: Seinfeld "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Michael Scott vows to end “100,000 years of being weirded out by gays” in “Gay Witch Hunt,” an episode of this sitcom that ends with Michael kissing Oscar Martinez in Dunder Mifflin Scranton’s conference room. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Of ice "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] In the “Puppy Episode” of her namesake sitcom, Ellen DeGeneres realizes that she is gay while speaking to a therapist played by this woman. In 30 Rock, Liz Lemon mistakes a teenage girl for this woman after mixing white wine with anti-anxiety pills. ","answer":"ANSWER: Oprah Winfrey [accept either] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this World War I campaign, in which bloody landings at ANZAC Cove forged a sense of national identity for Australians and New Zealanders. Mustafa Kemal commanded Turkish forces during this campaign. ","answer":"ANSWER: Gallipoli Campaign [or the Dardanelles Campaign; or the Battle of Çanakkale] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] This country memorializes the Battle of Vimy Ridge, the first time all four divisions of its WWI corps fought side-by-side. On its home front, Robert Borden dealt with a conscription crisis among Francophones in Quebec. ","answer":"ANSWER: Canada "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] During World War I, this South African field marshal occupied German South West Africa and chased Paul von Lettow-Vorbeck around East Africa. This United Party prime minister’s 1948 electoral defeat ushered in the apartheid era. ","answer":"ANSWER: Jan Smuts "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this American scientist. He names a butterfly-shaped attractor that came from his work in modeling atmospheric convection. ","answer":"ANSWER: Edward Lorenz [do not accept or prompt on “Lorentz”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] The Lorenz equations are known for having solutions that exhibit this phenomenon. This phenomenon, the extreme sensitivity of a system to initial conditions, is exhibited by the butterfly effect. ","answer":"ANSWER: chaos theory "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] One of these systems attached to another’s end is also known for exhibiting chaotic behavior. These systems, which are made of a weight suspended from a pivot, are examples of simple harmonic oscillators. ","answer":"ANSWER: (double) pendulums "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this Haitian author who included “Between the Pool and the Gardenias” in her collection Krik? Krak!. She chronicled Sophie Caco’s journey from Haiti to New York and back again in Breath, Eyes, Memory. ","answer":"ANSWER: Edwidge Danticat "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Alejo Carpentier wrote about a Haitian one of these people named Ti Noel in The Kingdom of this World. Harriet Jacobs and Olaudah Equiano both wrote narratives about their time as these people. ","answer":"ANSWER: slaves "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Aime Cesaire set his adaptation of this Shakespeare play in Haiti. Cesaire emphasized this play’s racial subtext by casting Prospero as white and Caliban as black. ","answer":"ANSWER: The Tempest "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this French pianist and music teacher whose students included Philip Glass, Quincy Jones, and Eliot Carter. ","answer":"ANSWER: Nadia Boulanger "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] During her tour of the United States, Boulanger premiered a Symphony for Organ and Orchestra composed by this former student of hers. He composed the ballets Rodeo and Appalachian Spring. ","answer":"ANSWER: Aaron Copland "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Boulanger encouraged her student Astor Piazzolla to compose music for this dance genre instead of classical music. This partner dance form originated in Argentina and Uruguay. ","answer":"ANSWER: tango "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"9. Earlier in its history, this island housed men like Whitey Bulger and Robert Stroud, who was known as its “birdman.” ","answer":"ANSWER: Alcatraz Island "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Dee Brown, who participated in the occupation of Alcatraz, wrote a history of the American West titled Bury My Heart at this location. Over 300 Lakota Sioux were killed in a 1890 massacre at this South Dakota location. ","answer":"ANSWER: Wounded Knee [or Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] This activist chronicled America’s history of broken treaties and forced Indian removals in A Century of Dishonor. Her novel Ramona is often credited with reigniting interest in California’s Spanish missions. ","answer":"ANSWER: Helen Hunt Jackson "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this queen of Connacht from the Ulster Cycle. In some accounts, this woman’s lover Fergus protects her with a shield as she fills a moat with urine. ","answer":"ANSWER: Queen Medb [mave] [or Queen Maeve; or Queen Medba] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Queen Medb was jealous of one of these animals, which she attacked in a “raid” at Cooley. In Greek mythology, Io turns into a white type of this animal after being courted by Zeus. ","answer":"ANSWER: cows [or cattle; accept synonyms] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] This warrior single-handedly opposed Medb’s army in the Cattle Raid of Cooley. This son of Lugh wields a barbed spear known as Gae Bulg. ","answer":"ANSWER: Cuchulainn [cuh-HOO-linn] [or Setanta] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this title character of Yann Martel’s most famous novel. This adherent of Christianity, Islam, and Hinduism spends 227 days adrift in the Pacific Ocean with a tiger named Richard Parker. ","answer":"ANSWER: Piscine Patel [accept either underlined name; or Life of Pi] [10] “One: A Poem” are the first words of this poem when it is translated into Pilish [“PILE-ish”], a language in which the number of letters in each word of a poem spell out the digits of pi. This Edgar Allan Poe poem features a bird that croaks “nevermore.” "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] A poet from this country wrote an ode to the “admirable number pi,” but is better known for “Love at First Sight.”Another of its writers analyzed the effect of Stalinism on this country in The Captive Mind. ","answer":"ANSWER: Poland (the first sentence refers to Wislawa Szymborska, while the second refers to Czesław Miłosz) "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this process, in which molecules of a liquid or gas adhere to a solid surface and form a thin film on it. ","answer":"ANSWER: adsorption [do not accept or prompt on “absorption”] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] The degree of adsorption can depend on this property, which quantifies how easily a surface can maintain contact with a liquid. Surfaces with a large value of this property usually form a very small contact angle with water. ","answer":"ANSWER: wettability [accept word forms; accept hydrophilicity and word forms] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Liquids with a high wettability often have a low value for this cohesive property. This property, which is reduced by surfactants, is what allows insects to walk on water. ","answer":"ANSWER: surface tension [or surface energy; prompt on gamma] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name this scholastic philosopher who expressed his disdain for lazily contradictory theology in Sic et Non. ","answer":"ANSWER: Peter Abelard [or Pierre Abélard] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Peter Abelard was a philosopher from this modern-day country, where another scholastic philosopher, Peter Lombard, taught at the cathedral school of Notre Dame. ","answer":"ANSWER: France "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Abelard’s infamous quarrels with other theologians include one with a man of this name from Laon. Another philosopher of this name was the archbishop of Canterbury and made an ontological proof of God’s existence. ","answer":"ANSWER: Anselm [or Saint Anselm of Canterbury or Anselm of Laon] Tiebreaker. The “Arctic” type of these animals is the most prominent predator of the lemming. For 10 points each: "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Name these animals whose “true” genus also includes a long-eared species called the fennec. ","answer":"ANSWER: foxes [or Vulpes] "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] Like wolves, foxes are in the family Canidae, which comes from the Latin for these animals. ","answer":"ANSWER: dogs "},{"tournament":"ACF Fall 2018","difficulty":"Difficulty: Easy College","round":"E","question":"[10] The red fox has been labeled as a highly damaging invasive species in this country, whose other invasive species include the cane toad. ","answer":"ANSWER: Australia"}]
